Rosa Smith Eigenmann papers, 1870-1930 C59
Indiana University Archives
Rosa Smith Eigenmann papers
1870-1951 and undated
bulk 1880-1928
Indiana University Archives
Eigenmann, Rosa Smith, 1858-1947
C59
2 cubic feet 5 dc
Rosa Smith Eigenmann was an internationally known ichthyologist and attended Indiana University from 1880-1882. The Rosa Smith Eigenmann papers include some of her correspondence, research, and family ephemera.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Advance notice is required.
Biographical Note
Rosa Smith was born on October 7, 1858 to Lucretia and Charles Kendall Smith in Monmouth, Illinois. The family moved to San Diego, California in 1876. She completed her secondary education at the Point Loma Seminary in San Diego and also attended a five-week course at a business college in San Francisco. Smith had a lifelong interest in natural history and became the first woman to be a full member of the San Diego Society of Natural History. In 1879, she met David Starr Jordan, a professor of natural history at Indiana University, who invited her to study at IU. Smith studied at IU for two years and spent the summer of 1880 touring Europe with Professor Jordan and other students and faculty from IU. Family obligations caused Smith to return to San Diego in 1882 before completing her undergraduate degree.
After returning to San Diego, Smith continued her studies of fish including the blind goby fish she discovered. She published several articles that provided formal descriptions of various species of fish. Smith also worked as a journalist and as a secretary and librarian for the San Diego Society of Natural History. While at IU, she met Carl Eigenmann who was working on his Ph.D. The two continued to correspond after she returned to San Diego, and they were married at Smith's home on August 20, 1887. The Eigenmanns often collaborated with each other on their scientific research and published numerous articles together. After their marriage, they went to Harvard University where they studied the Agassiz collections of fish. Smith was also granted special student status at Harvard to study cryptogamic botany from 1887-1888. In 1889, the Eigenmanns returned to California where they established a biological station and continued their studies of fish in the region. They also held appointments as curators at the California Academy of Sciences. Additionally, the Eigenmanns spent considerable time in South America studying and collecting freshwater fish.
In 1891, the Eigenmanns returned to Bloomington, Indiana when Carl was appointed Professor of Zoology at Indiana University. Carl was later named chair of the Department of Zoology and the first Dean of the Graduate School. The Eigenmanns had five children: Lucretia Margaretha Eigenmann, Charlotte Elizabeth Eigenmann, Theodore Smith Eigenmann, Adele Rosa Eigenmann, and Thora Marie Eigenmann. Family responsibilities prevented Rosa from continuing her own research, but she worked as an editor for her husband's papers. In 1926, the Eigenmanns left Indiana and returned to San Diego. Carl Eigenmann died on April 24, 1927. Rosa continued to live in the San Diego area until her death on January 12, 1947 of chronic myocarditis after a series of difficult eye operations.
Rosa Smith Eigenmann was one of the first women ichthyologists. Eigenmann authored twelve papers on her own and co-authored twenty-five articles with her husband. The Eigenmanns have been credited with the identification of 35 new genera of fish and descriptions of almost 150 species of fish. Additionally, Rosa Smith Eigenmann is believed to be the first woman allowed to attend graduate-level classes at Harvard University, the first woman president of IU's Sigma Xi (an honorary science society) chapter, and the first woman to determine a new species of fish.
Arrangement
This collection has been organized into three series: Correspondence (1871-1941 and undated), Ephemera (1880-1951 and undated), and Research (1880 and undated). Each series is arranged chronologically.
Scope and Content Note
This collection is divided into three series: Correspondence, 1880-1941 and undated; Ephemera, 1880-1951 and undated; and Research, 1880 and undated. The Correspondence series consists mainly of letters exchanged between Rosa Smith Eigenmann and her family. Common correspondents include Carl H. Eigenmann (Rosa's husband), Adele Eigenmann (Rosa's second-youngest child), Mary Smith Berry (Rosa's sister), and Lucretia Smith (Rosa's mother). The series also features correspondence of David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann about professional and personal interests. The Ephemera series contains items collected by Rosa Smith Eigenmann and her family, including an invitation to the IU Commencement in 1886. The Research series contains three texts written by Rosa Smith Eigenmann.
Separated Material
Photographs transferred to Archives Photograph Collection.
Related Material
For the papers of Rosa's husband, Carl Eigenmann, see IU Archives Collection C63. The Lilly Library at Indiana University has a collection of Carl and Rosa Smith Eigenmanns' papers: Eigenmann mss.,1851-1971. Additional papers of Rosa Smith Eigenmann are held at the Smithsonian Institution Archives: Rosa Smith Eigenmann Papers, 1845, 1884-1939, 1970, 1973.
Acquisition Information
Accessions 9297, 2021/144, and 2022/015.
Custodial History
Accession 9297 was transferred to Indiana University archives at an unknown date. Accessions 2021/144 and 2022/015 were purchased 2021-2022.
Women ichthyologists --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; Women ichthyologists --Indiana --Bloomington --Correspondence.; Women ichthyologists --California --San Diego --Archives.; Women ichthyologists --California --San Diego --Correspondence.; Fishes --Research --California --San Diego --Sources.; Eigenmann, Carl H., 1863-1927; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931 -- Correspondence; Eigenmann, Rosa Smith, 1858-1947 -- Archives; Eigenmann, Rosa Smith, 1858-1947 -- Correspondence
- Correspondence, 1870-1941, undated
  - Charles K. Smith to "Cousin Clarissa and Husband", December 25, 1870 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, August 12, 1875 (Box 1)
  - Joseph Gray (grandfather) (?) to Charles K. Smith, August 18, 1875 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, August 15-16, 1875 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, April 13, 1880s (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, February 16, 1880 (Box 1)
  - Charles H. Gilbert to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, March 1, 1880 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, March 4, 1880 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, March 22, 1880 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, April 2, 1880 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, April 15, 1880 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, April 21, 1880 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, April 22, 1880; handwritten copy (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, April 23, 1880; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, April 29, 1880 (Box 1)
  - Goodall Perkins & Co. General Agents to David Starr Jordan, May 1, 1880 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, May 3, 1880 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, May 9, 1880 (?) (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, May 13, 1880 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, June 7, 1880 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, August 12, 1880 (Box 1)
  - Charles H. Gilbert to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, August 12, 1880 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, October 6, 1880 (Box 1)
  - Charles H. Gilbert to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, October 7, 1880 (Box 1)
  - Charles H. Gilbert to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, October 14, 1880 (Box 1)
  - Charles H. Gilbert to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, October 27, 1880 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, December 2, 1880 (Box 1)
  - Charles H. Gilbert to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, December 22, 1880 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, December 24, 1880 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, December 29, 1880 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, circa 1880? (Box 1)
  - Daniel Cleveland to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, February 11, 1881 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, February 18, 1881 (Box 1)
  - Smithsonian Institution to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, February 28, 1881 (Box 1)
  - J. Russell Smith to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, June 4, 1881 (Box 1)
  - Kate O. Sessions to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, June 5, 1881 (Box 1)
  - Kate O. Sessions to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, October 9, 1881 (Box 1)
  - Kate O. Sessions to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, October 30, 1881 (Box 1)
  - Mary B. McCalla to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, December 2, 1881 (Box 1)
  - Kate O. Sessions to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, December 26, 1881 (Box 1)
  - J. Russell Smith to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, March 4, 1882 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, April 24, 1882 (Box 1)
  - W.G.W Harford, California Academy of Sciences, to RSE, July 23, 1882 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, July 29, 1882 (Box 1)
  - W.G.W. Harford, California Academy of Sciences, to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, August 1, 1882 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, October 16, 1882 (Box 1)
  - Smithsonian Institution to David Starr Jordan re: Rosa Smith Eigenmann, October 28, 1882 (Box 1)
  - W.G.W. Harford, California Academy of Sciences, to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, December 18, 1882 (Box 1)
  - California Academy of Sciences to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, December 18, 1882 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to David Starr Jordan, March 17, 1883; handwritten copy (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, April 6, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Kate O. Sessions to [Rosa Smith Eigenmann], June 19, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, June 21, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, June 27, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, June 29, 1883
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, circa June-July 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, July 3, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, July 5, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, July 8, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, July 10, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, July 13-14, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, July 15, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, July 16, 1883 (Box 1)
  - W.G.W. Harford, California Academy of Sciences, to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, July 16, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, July 18, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, July 19, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, July 23, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, July 26, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, July 30, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Cordelia S. Kirkland to May B. West, July 30-August 2, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, July 31, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, circa July 1883; letter 1 of 3 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, circa July 1883; letter 2 of 3 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, circa July 1883; letter 3 of 3 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, August 2, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, August 6, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, August 8, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, August 11, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to M (Mary Smith Berry?), August 19, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, August 20, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, August 24, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, August 29, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, August 31, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, September 6, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, September 15, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, September 20, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, October 1, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, October 4-5, 1883 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, November 11, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, December 16, 1883 (Box 1)
  - W.G.W. Harford, California Academy of Sciences, to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, December 17, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Charles H. Gilbert to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, December 20, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, 1883? (Box 1)
  - W.G.W. Harford, California Academy of Sciences, to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, January 8, 1884 (Box 1)
  - W.G.W. Harford, California Academy of Sciences, to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, January 14, 1884 (Box 1)
  - W.G.W. Harford, California Academy of Sciences, to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, January 29, 1884 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, February 15, 1884 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, March 2, 1884 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, March 28, 1884 (Box 1)
  - W.G.W. Harford, California Academy of Sciences, to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, July 18, 1884 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, September 3, 1884 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, circa September 1884; 5 postcards 5 postcards (Box 1)
  - W.G.W. Harford, California Academy of Sciences, to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, December 3, 1884 (Box 1)
  - Kate O. Sessions to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, December 24-25, 1884 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, December 26-27, 1884 (Box 1)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, January 14, 1885 (Box 2)
  - Kate O. Sessions to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, January 17, 1885 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, November 21, 1885 (Box 2)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, November 30, 1885 (Box 2)
  - Caroline C. Jackson, Pacific Association of Collegiate Alumnae, to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, circa 1885-1886 (Box 2)
  - Kate O. Sessions to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, April 21, 1886 (Box 2)
  - Pacific Association of Collegiate Alumnae (Kate O. Sessions) to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, April 30, 1886 (Box 2)
  - W.G.W. Harford, California Academy of Sciences, to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, June 11, 1886 (Box 2)
  - Kate O. Sessions to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, July 4, 1886 (Box 2)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, October 4, 1886 (Box 2)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann(?), circa 1886 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith and Mary Smith Berry, February 12, 1887 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to unknown - Missing, April 1887? (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, September 18, 1887 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Smith family, September 18, 1887 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Smith family, September 25, 1887 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Smith family, October 3, 1887 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann and Carl H. Eigenmann to Smith family, October 9, 1887 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, October 16, 1887 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Smith family, October 23, 1887 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to unknown ("My dear Friend"), October 23, 1887 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith and Mary Smith Berry, October 26, 1887 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann and Carl H. Eigenmann to Charles K. Smith (father), October 30, 1887 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Smith family, November 1, 1887 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Smith family, November 17, 1887 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Smith family, November 25, 1887 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, November 28-30, 1887 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Smith family, December 27, 1887 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, January 3, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, January 22, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to J. R. Berry and Mary Smith Berry, January 25, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K.Smith, Lucretia Smith, and Mary Smith Berry, January 30, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Smith family, February 5, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Smith family, February 12, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, February 19, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Henry C. Cook to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, February 20, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Henry C. Cook to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, February 24, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, February 26, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to unknown, circa February 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, March 4, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Smith family, March 11, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Smith family, March 25, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, April 2, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann and Carl H. Eigenmann to Smith family, April 8, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann and Carl H. Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, April 15, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, April 24, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Zella R. Cronyn to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, April 30, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Smith family, May 2, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann and Carl H. Eigenmann to Smith family, May 9, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann and Carl H. Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, May 11, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Abby H. Patton(?) to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, May 14, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, May 19, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, May 24, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann and Carl H. Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, May 27, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, circa May 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Smith family, June 3, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Allie A. Smith to Lucretia Smith, July 2, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann and Carl H. Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, August 5, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, August 22, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to unknown, 1888? (Box 2)
  - David Starr Jordan to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, 1891 or later (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, April 10, 1892 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to "Sister" (Mary Smith Berry?), April 16, 1892 (Box 2)
  - A.G. Kendall to Charles K. Smith, December 10, 1892 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, December 19, 1892 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, April 3, 1893 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Marshall McDonald, Commisioner Fish & Fisheries, June 20, 1893 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, July 2, 1893 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, circa August 2-17, 1893 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, August 18, 1893 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, August 20, 1893 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, August 20, 1893 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, August 22, 1893 (Box 2)
  - B.W. Evermann to Mr. Rathburn(?), November 22, 1893 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, circa 1893-1894 (Box 2)
  - E.R. Parry to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, circa January 31, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, June 26, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, June 27, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, June 27, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, June 28, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, July 1, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, July 2, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, July 3, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, July 4, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, July 6, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, July 7, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, July 8-11, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, July 12, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, July 12, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, July 14, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, July 14, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, July 17, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, July 18, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, July 21, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, July 22, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, July 24, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, July 27, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, July 27, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, July 28, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, July 29(?), 1894 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, July 29-30, 1894 (Box 2)
  - David Starr Jordan to Carl H. Eigenmann, July 31, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, circa June-July 1894 (Box 2)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann and children, August 14-15, 1894 (Box 3)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, August 17, 1894 (Box 3)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, August 18, 1894 (Box 3)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, August 19-20, 1894 (Box 3)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, August 22, 1894 (Box 3)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, August 23, 1894 (Box 3)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, August 24, 1894 (Box 3)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, August 26, 1894 (Box 3)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, August 29, 1894 (Box 3)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, August 31, 1894 (Box 3)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, September 5-9, 1894 (Box 3)
  - Charles K. Smith (father) to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, October 22, 1894 (Box 3)
  - Lucretia Smith to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, October 22, 1894 (Box 3)
  - Laura O. Talbott, National Science Club for Women, to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, February 20, 1895 (Box 3)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, February 22, [1895] (Box 3)
  - E. R. Parry to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, March 30, 1895 (Box 3)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, April 23, 1895 (Box 3)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Charles K. and Lucretia Smith, July 24, 1895 (Box 3)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, May 13, 1896 (Box 3)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, July 5, 1896 (Box 3)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Lucretia Smith, July 14, 1896 (Box 3)
  - John W. Hoyt (University of the United States Committee) to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, August 9, 1897 (Box 3)
  - R. I. Hamilton, IU Board of Trustees, to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, November 28, 1898 (Box 3)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to David Starr Jordan, May 16, 1899
  - Margaret Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, June 16, 1899 (Box 3)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, June 25, 1899 (Box 3)
  - Carl H. Eigenmann to Rosa Smith Eigenmann, July 5, 1899 (Box 3)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, July 6, 1899 (Box 3)
  - Rosa Smith Eigenmann to Carl H. Eigenmann, July 9, 1899 (Box 3)